John Fischetti Cartoons
John Fischetti Cartoons
1962-1978
1962-1967
Fischetti, John R.
1.3 linear ft.
Original editorial cartoons by the Pulitzer Prize-winning cartoonist
2652423
Biographical History
John Fischetti (1916-1980) was an American Pulitzer Prize winning editorial cartoonist.
Born in Brooklyn, New York on September 27, 1916, John R. Fischetti was the son of an Italian barber. In his teens during the Great Depression, Fischetti traveled the country doing odd jobs. For a period of time, Fischetti worked in a hotel where one of his influences, cartoonist Rollin Kirby lived.
After spending three years studying at the Pratt Institute (1937-1940), Fischetti moved to California and worked for Disney Studios for nine months until he began to suffer from eye strain. He then pursued freelance work and ended up in Chicago as a cartoonist at the Chicago Sun in 1941. His freelance work appeared in publications including Esquire, the Saturday Evening Post and Collier's.
Fischetti then served from 1942 to 1945 as a radio operator and Army sergeant in Europe during World War II. He worked for Stars and Stripes from 1945 to 1946 with Dick Wingert among other World War II cartoonists. Fischetti then held the position of cartoonist for the New York Herald Tribune for two years, leaving for the Newspaper Enterprise Association syndicate where he stayed until 1962 when he went back to the New York Herald Tribune. During this time, Fischetti sought to combine the humor cartoon with the editorial cartoon and felt the Herald Tribune was a good fit for his work. His work was syndicated through the Publisher's Newspaper Syndicate.
In 1967, Fischetti left New York for the Chicago Daily News after the Herald Tribune folded where he was chief political cartoonist until 1978 when that paper went out of business. His final position was cartoonist for the Chicago Sun-Times which he held until his death in 1980.
Fischetti's cartoons were recognized with many awards. A Pulitzer Prize for editorial cartooning was awarded to Fischetti in 1969 not for a particular cartoon but for the body of his 1968 work. He also received two Sigma Delta Chi awards (1956, 1958) and an American Civil Liberties award. Fischetti was also an active member of the National Cartoonists Society and received the Silver T-Square award in 1973 and the NCS's best editorial cartoon award four straight years from 1962 to 1965. A book of his cartoons, Zinga Zinga Za, was published in 1973.
John R. Fischetti died on November 18, 1980. Following his death, the Fischetti Endowment was started at Columbia College in Chicago. The endowment provides scholarships to journalism students and monetary awards to editorial cartoonists through the annual Fischetti Editorial Cartoon Competition.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Fischetti Cartoons consists of more than a hundred original editorial cartoons from the New York Herald Tribune (1962-1967), and one from the Chicago Sun-Times (1978). Approximately half of the cartoons are dated with years only; the remainder are undated. Each bears a copyright notice from either the New York Herald Tribune or the Publishers Newspaper Syndicate and various notations appear in the margins in pencil and crayon. Fischetti primarily worked in pen and ink on illustration board with screening.
Fischetti's cartoons mix politics and current events with social humor. His cartoons were syndicated widely and the majority focus on national and global events with a handful addressing issues local to New York City (the few local-oriented cartoons address the election of Mayor John Lindsay and the 1965 blackout). Many of the cartoons reflect the style of magazine cartoons and many depict unnamed figures commenting on current events in a humorous fashion. Of particular interest are Fischetti's cartoons that drew attention to the emergence of right-wing Republicans a s well as the racist influence of the Ku Klux Klan and the civil rights movement.
Arrangement of the Collection
The cartoons are arranged chronologically by year with undated cartoons located at the end of the collection. Within each year, the cartoons are arranged alphabetically by caption.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Fischetti, John R.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; New York herald tribune.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- New York (N.Y.); Civil rights movements -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Communism -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- New York (N.Y.); Political cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Fischetti, 1967.
1978 cartoon, gift of Betty Bewley, 2020.
Inventory
- Cartoons, 101 items 10 1/2 x 14 1/2"
  - Cartoons, 1962 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
    Achievements
  - Cartoons, 1963 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
    Elections returns
    The Fat cats and the canary
    If you keep insisting the world is round, people will really think we're the lunatic fringe.
    Wallace reaps the whirlwind
    What do you mean the town's had enough of this drunken crowd? I'm not drunk.
  - Cartoons, 1964 (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
    And leave the driving to us
    Barry certainly makes a handsome couple.
    Barry, you have a special charm of your own for democrats.
    Buddy system
    The country's in capable hands, dammit.
    I can say without fear of contradiction -- It stinks.
    I just want the Senate to put on its thinking cap during the civil rights debate.
    It's a heady wine -- domestic, of course.
  - Cartoons, 1964 (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
    Now he belongs to the Dark Ages.
    Phoenix
    Reduce to a cinder, then serve.
    The road back
    Rocky '64
    Sometimes I just feel like hanging up my sneakers.
    Sure tells you about the light bill going down but not a word about the phone bill going up.
    Watch your language. My friend here speaks war fluently.
    You're guilty of a serious personality cult offense -- taking all those pictures of me that I ordered.
  - Cartoons, 1965 (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
    --And I was so looking forward to the day when discrimination would end for him.
    Cannon to right of them, cannon to left of them...volley'd and thunder'd...
    Capital hill
    Cliff-hanger
    The Cocoon
    Flotsam
    How to ruin property values in Alabama
  - Cartoons, 1965 (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
    I didn't know Pop could hot dog.
    If it's too hot, I'll be happy to help you out of the kitchen.
    If they thought blasting the monuments was tough, destroying the ideas they represent is impossible.
    If you put it that way, Lyndon, how can I say no?
    I had no idea chess was so hazardous.
    Imagine that, Pop! Nazi bullies used to attack religious people out in the street...
    In the movies a guy's always cast away with a beautiful girl.
    It looked better on Nikita.
    It should be made absolutely clear to General Khanh that we vote for our leaders here... when we vote.
  - Cartoons, 1965 (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
    Let there be light...
    Life will be impossible with him if Americans are kept from coming here...Pierre so enjoys snapping at them.
    Marge, I think it's high time I stopped stalling on that trip abroad I've been promising you for so long.
    Men, nobody else is -- but Governor Wallace's mighty proud of you.
    Old habits are hard to break.
    The potting shed
    Those poor Dominicans...Castro's trying to make them as happy as he's made us.
    War monger!
    What does he think we are -- capitalists?
    Why, it's against everything I believe in -- it's constructive.
    You're jostling me. Can't you walk without stumbling?
  - Cartoons, 1966-1967 (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
    Feeding the flames of bigotry
    Home of the brave
    Practice makes imperfect
  - Cartoons, 1978; includes note from Fischetti to Betty Bewley (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
    Gift of Betty Bewley, 2020.
    First canal treaty victory the hard way
  - Cartoons, A-H, Undated (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
    -- About the caustic calls of 'Author! Author!'...we are not amused.
    After all, you must remember I'm an opportunist.
    The Alabama volunteers
    Algerian strong man
    All hot -- there aren't any cool lines.
    Anti-war is hell, man.
    But I don't want to get well.
    Can't you realize what a frightful spectacle you're making of yourself?
    Fur lined foxhole (see Undated, miscellaneous)
    Gordian knot
    The great anti-American sport-reducing the strike zone.
    He went that-a-way.
    Highway blight
  - Cartoons, I-M, Undated (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
    I certainly hope they don't expect us to explain us.
    If they do discover life on Mars it'll probably be underdeveloped.
    I hear we're setting all kinds of records.
    I know a golden opportunity when I see one.
    I'll give that plane just one eon...
    I'm having a re-entry problem.
    I want to thank all the good people of Alabama who stood silently by.
    Killed in action
    Lieutenant -- The Viet Cong had a 'Teach-in' here. They killed the village chief, some men and a kid.
    Look, fellas -- I don't want the moon. I'll just settle for what's left.
    Looks like a long run -- they got rave reviews.
    Men, there's no place to go but up.
    Most welcome, Pope Paul
  - Cartoons, N-T, Undated (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
    Name a clean one
    Nothing to lose but your temper
    Now, that's what I call latitudes and longitudes.
    Redoubt
    Sanctuary
    Sentence - six more year (see Undated, miscellaneous)
    Since Stalin has been partially rehabilitated his portrait was replaced facing the wall, of course.
    The Spoilers
    Strongman
    Testament
    That was a pretty good preliminary, kid -- meet the main event.
    They better not have another power failure. A little blackout camaraderie goes a long way with me.
    Trouble with Guevara was, he didn't care which side my bread's buttered on.
    Tug of war
  - Cartoons, U-Y, Undated (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
    The Ugly American
    The Unholy Grail
    We have a lot in common...she loathes my work and I abhor hers.
    We want you to share our way of, er, life.
    When all about you kept their heads, you lost yours -- Why?
    Where seldom's heard an encouraging word.
    The whites sure are preserving the Northern way of life.
    Won't it be nice to have me nagging you again, now that L.B.J. won't?
    You have a nerve voicing an opinion -- are you trying to undermine Democracy?
    You're so right -- leave us alone and we guarantee peace and quiet here.
  - Cartoons, miscellaneous, Undated (Oversize 3)
    Fur lined foxhole
    Sentence - six more years
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Alabama B1F2 B1F5-B1F7 B2F1-B2F2
Algeria B2F1
Americans B1F7
Argentina B3
armed forces B1F5 B3
Asia B1F7
Baker, Bobby B1F3 B2F1
Ben Bella, Ahmed B2F1
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B1F6-B1F7
Britain B2F4
Buckley, William B1F4
capitalism B1F7
Castro, Fidel B1F2 B1F7 B2F3
China B1F7 B2F4
civil rights B1F2-B1F4 B1F6-B1F7 B2F1-B2F4
communism B1F1-B1F2 B1F5-B1F7 B2F1 B2F3-B2F4
Congress B1F3-B1F4 B1F6 B2F1-B2F2 B2F4
crime B1F2 B2F3
Cyprus B1F4-B1F5
de Gaulle, Charles B1F7 B2F2
democracy B2F4
demonstrations B1F7-B1F8 B2F1-B2F2 B2F4
developing countries B2F2
discrimination B1F5 B2F4
Dominican Republic B1F7 B2F1
elections B1F2-B1F3
Erhard, Ludwig B1F6
foreign policy B1F3 B2F4
France B1F7
Free Society Association B1F3
Fulbright, J. William B1F7
Goldberg, Arthur B2F2
Goldwater, Barry B1F2-B1F4
Great Society B1F5
guerilla warfare B2F1
Guevara, Che B2F3
Ho Chi Minh B1F5-B1F7
hope B2F3
India-Pakistan War B2F1-B2F2
Indonesia B2F1
Jim Crow B2F4
John Birch Society B1F2 B2F2
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F3 B1F5-B1F7 B2F1-B2F4
journalism B2F1
justice B2F2
Khanh, Nguyen B1F6
Khrushchev, Nikita B1F4 B1F6 B2F3
Kosygin, Alexey B1F6
Ku Klux Klan B1F5 B2F2 B2F4
leisure B2F3
Lenin, Vladimir B2F3
Lindsay, John B1F4 B2F3
mafia B1F2
mainstream politics B1F4
Makarios III B1F4-B1F5
Marx, Karl B2F3
Meredith, James B1F8
Middle East B2F2
Mississippi B1F3 B1F8
Nazism B1F6 B2F4
New York City B2F3
Nixon, Richard M. B1F5 B1F8
nuclear weapons B1F7
parents B1F6
peace B1F7 B2F2
Peron, Juan B3
police B1F7 B2F1
police brutality B1F7
Pope Paul VI B2F2
power failure B2F3-B2F4
race B2F4
racism B1F3 B1F5-B1F6 B1F8-B2F2 B2F4
religion B1F6
Republican Party B1F3-B1F6 B2F2
Rhodesia B2F4
right-wing extremists B1F2 B1F4 B1F6
riots B1F8 B2F3
Rockefeller, Nelson B1F2 B1F4
Russia B1F7
Schweitzer, Albert B2F3
Soviet Union B1F3 B1F5 B2F2-B2F4
space exploration B1F1 B1F7 B2F2
Stalin, Joseph B2F3
steel industry B2F3
Sukarno B2F1
terrorists B1F5
tourism B1F7
Ulbricht, Walter B1F4
unions B1F3 B2F4
United Nations B1F4 B1F6 B2F1-B2F3
utility bills B1F4
Venezuela B1F2
Vietnam War B1F5-B1F7 B2F1-B2F4
voting rights B1F5
Wallace, George B1F2-B1F3 B1F7
Zedong, Mao B1F7 B2F1-B2F4